# **TIJU MATHEW GEORGE**

806-789-2481 • tiju.m.george@gmail.com • <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/george-tiju">http://www.linkedin.com/in/george-tiju</a> • <a href="mailto:github.com/tijugeorge">github.com/tijugeorge</a> New Hyde Park, NY

### **SUMMARY**

Self-motivated, results-driven software engineer and technically sound MIS and Computer Science Masters graduate. Experienced in Python programming and can adjust to other languages. Keen to learn new skills, tools and ability to adjust to demanding projects.

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

**Programming:** Python, C++, SQL, Java **Front-End**: HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, JavaScript

Databases: Microsoft SQL Server, NoSQL- PostgreSQL, Oracle 11g, Hadoop

OS and Tools: Windows 7/8/10, Linux (Ubuntu), Google App Engine, Jinja, MatLab, SAS EM & EG, Eclipse, Flask, Tensorflow

Cloud and Visualization: MS Azure, Google Cloud data store, OpenCV, Gephi, Tableau

#### **PROJECTS**

Movie Trailer Website (Python, HTML, CSS) - https://github.com/tijugeorge/Movie-trailer-website

- Server-side code written in Python to store a list of my favorite movies, including box art imagery and a movie trailer URL.
- This data is then served to a web page using HTML and CSS allowing visitors to review these movies and watch the trailers.

Multi-user Blog (Python, Google App Engine, SQL, cryptography standards like MD5, SHA2, HMAC used)-

# https://multi-user-blog-163400.appspot.com/

- A multi user blog where users can sign in & post blog posts as well as 'Like' & 'Comment' on other posts made on the blog.
- Hosted this blog on Google App Engine and created an authentication system for users to be able to register and sign in and then create blog posts.

Sudoku with Artificial Intelligence (Python) - https://github.com/tijugeorge/Artificial-Intelligence/tree/master/Sudoku with AI

- Designed Al-agent that solves the sudoku puzzles which is part of the Nanodegree
- Use of constraint propagation to solve the sudoku problem.

Social Network Analysis using Facebook API (Python-textblob, matplotlib) - <a href="https://github.com/tijugeorge/Project-">https://github.com/tijugeorge/Project-</a>

2/blob/master/Project-2/Prescriptive-Analytics.pdf

- Used the Facebook community page for online live comments analysis for data mining.
- Sentiment analysis done on the retrieved data using the python and its ML packages.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Software Engineer Systems, HPE (Aspire Systems Inc.), Tallahassee, FL

Sept 2016 - Present

- Research, design and later implement python codes to the testing environment and preparation of technical documentation.
- Created reports on the test cases and requirement traceability matrix and log issues depending on the test cases in agile environment.
- Worked on retrieving, updating and manipulating healthcare data for data analysis and preparing test automation cases.
- Investigate, identify root cause of performance by evaluating; recommending solutions to systems of Florida Healthcare Medicaid interchange (UI) payments and complying with HIPAA regulations.
- Worked on test cases and deployed in model office which is a prototype of production systems and monitor the changes in TDD environment.

Teaching Assistant/IT Student Analyst, Texas Tech University-IT Division, Lubbock, TX

Dec 2014- May 2016

- Served as teaching aide for class of 40 students when professor went to conferences; graded and supervise examinations.
- Worked as technical analyst for IT Division by providing front line technical support to Staff, Faculty & students with daily closure of 15-20 tickets on priority basis.
- Troubleshot computer network and communication protocols including TCP/IP, UDP & HTTP.

# Process Expert, Maersk, IN

Feb 2014 – Jun 2014

- Designed and created backend data access modules using PL/SQL stored procedures and Oracle.
- Assisted software development team with various SDLC stages in agile environment & documenting technical specifications.

# Intern Embedded Systems, ThinkLabs TechnoSolutions, IN

Insight into different micro-controller architectures and their programming using Embedded C.

July 2011

• Interfaced different sensors, display and learnt communication protocols like UART, SPI, Analog signal processing using DC and built specific code libraries for ATmega128 microcontroller.

# **EDUCATION**

Texas Tech University, TX - Master of Science in Management Information Systems-Data Science

May 2016

Coursework: Decision Theory and Business Analytics, Data and Text Mining, Prescriptive Analysis, Business Problem Solving, Database Concepts, Statistical Concepts (regression, gradient boosting), Data management and Business Intelligence

University of Mumbai, India - Undergraduate in Computer Science, Physics

May 2012

Coursework: Distributed Computing, Algorithm and Data Structures, Compiler Design, Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning, Image and Digital Signal processing, DBMS, Optimization Techniques and Embedded Systems.

## **Udacity - Artificial Intelligence Nanodegree**

in progress

### **EXTRA-CURRICULAR & AWARDS**

- Volunteer tutor at Institutional Diversity, Equity & Community serving the Lubbock area, TX.
- Secretarial Coordinator for Big Data Symposium at Texas Tech University 2016.